NIANLONG LI

+86 156-1156-6201 ♦ nianlong2016@iscas.ac.cn ♦ nianlongl.com Institute of Software, Chinese Academy of Sciences 4# South Fourth Street, Zhong Guan Cun, Beijing, 100190, China

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am a 5th-year PhD student in the Beijing Key Lab of Human-Computer Interaction at the Institute of Software, Chinese Academy of Sciences (ISCAS), advised by Prof. Feng Tian and Associate Prof. Teng Han. My research interests lie in the area of human-computer interaction (HCI), focusing on interaction techniques in virtual and augmented reality (VR/AR), understanding and modeling human behaviors. Before coming to ISCAS, I completed my B.S. degree in Software Engineering at Xiangtan University in 2016.

Research Interests: VR/AR Interaction, Haptics and Illusions, Multimodal Interaction, Human Behaviors Modeling

EDUCATION

University of Chinese Academy of Sciences

Sep 2016 - Present

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Advisor: Feng Tian

Xiangtan University

Sep 2012 - Jul 2016

B.Sc. in Software Engineering

PUBLICATIONS

Conference Papers

- [C.7]. Nianlong Li, Zhengquan Zhang, Can Liu, Zengyao Yang*, Yinan Fu, Feng Tian, Teng Han, Mingming Fan. vMirror: Enhancing the Interaction with Occluded or Distant Objects in VR with Virtual Mirrors. Proceedings of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '21).
- [C.6]. Nianlong Li, Han-Jong Kim, Luyao Shen, Feng Tian, Teng Han*, Xing-Dong Yang, Tek-Jin Nam. HapLinkage: Prototyping Haptic Proxies for Virtual Hand Tools Using Linkage Mechanism. Proceedings of the 33nd Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST '20). Best Paper Honorable Mention Award (Top 5%).
- [C.5]. Nianlong Li, Teng Han*, Feng Tian, Jin Huang, Minghui Sun, Pourang Irani, Jason Alexander. Get a Grip: Evaluating Grip Gestures for VR Input using a Lightweight Pen. Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20). Best Paper Honorable Mention Award (Top 5%).
- [C.4]. Jin Huang, Feng Tian*, Nianlong Li, Xiangmin Fan. Modeling the Uncertainty in 2D Moving Target Selection. Proceedings of the 32nd Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST '19).
- [C.3]. Nianlong Li, Feng Tian*, Jin Huang, Xiangmin Fan, Hongan Wang. 2D-BayesPointer: An Implicit Moving Target Selection Technique Enabled by Human Performance Modeling. Extended Abstracts of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '18).
- [C.2]. Qikun Ma, Shiyang Wang, Jie Liu*, **Nianlong Li**. InteractiveSubtitle: Subtitle Interaction for Language Learning. *Proceedings of the Sixth International Symposium of Chinese CHI* (ChineseCHI '18).
- [C.1]. Yunzhi Li, Yinan Xu, Xiang Li, Jie Liu*, Nianlong Li. TapFlick: Combining Tap and Flick for Text Entry on Touchscreen Devices. Proceedings of the Sixth International Symposium of Chinese CHI (ChineseCHI '18).

Journal Articles

- [J.3]. **Nianlong Li**, Jin Huang, Feng Tian*, Guozhong Dai, Hongan Wang. Monitoring motor symptoms in Parkinson's disease via instrumenting daily artifacts with inertia sensors. *CCF Transactions on Pervasive Computing and Interaction* 1.2 (2019): 100-113.
- [J.2]. **Nianlong Li**, Jin Huang, Feng Tian*, Guozhong Dai, Hongan Wang. ICOMDT: An Interaction Computational Model for Dynamic Task. *Journal of Software*, 2019 (10): 2.
- [J.1]. Wei Sun, Jin Huang, **Nianlong Li**, Xiangmin Fan, Feng Tian*, Guozhong Dai, Hongan Wang. BCI Assisted Dynamic Target Selection Technique. *Journal of Software*, 2018, 29(Suppl.(2)): 108–119.

PATENTS

- [P.3]. A Target Selection Technology in 3D Environment based on Motion Trend Information. Feng Tian, Nianlong Li, Jin Huang, Hongan Wang. Filed: 2020-06-29. Patent No. CN 2020106088083.
- [P.2]. A Data Processing Method and Diagnostic Device for Assisting Disease Diagnosis based on Daily Necessities. Feng Tian, Xiangmin Fan, Nianlong Li, Junjun Fan, Hongan Wang. Filed: 2018-12-12. Patent No. CN 2018115182867.
- [P.1]. A Moving Target Selection Technology based on Correction of User Performance Model. Jin Huang, **Nianlong Li**, Feng Tian, Hongan Wang Filed: 2018-06-01. Patent No. CN 2018105586224.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages Software & Tools C#, C/C++, Java, Python, JavaScript/ThreeJS MATLAB, Unity3D, SPSS, LaTeX

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Enhancing VR Input and Haptic Feedback

Jun 2019 - Sep 2020

Supervisor: Prof. Feng Tian & Assoc. Prof. Teng Han

- · Investigated the potential of using a pen to afford more precise and dexterous input operations in VR.
- · Designed an interactive widget—vMirror—using mirror to alleviate occlusion and DOF issues with raycasting techniques in VR.
- · Designed a prototyping framework that provides typical motion templates and haptic renderers to facilitate proxy design of virtual hand tools.

Modeling the Uncertainty of Moving Target Selection

Aug 2017 - Apr 2019

Supervisor: Prof. Feng Tian & Asst. Prof. Jin Huang

- · Extended the Ternary-Gaussian model in 2D moving target selection tasks, and built an implicit target selection technique 2D-BayesPointer
- · Designed a ray-casting selection technique leveraging the characteristics of motion process to assit moving target selection in VR.

Monitoring Motor Symptoms in Parkinson's disease

May 2018 - Sep 2018

Supervisor: Prof. Feng Tian & Assoc. Prof. Xiangmin Fan

· Combined the IMU sensors with the daily artifacts to monitor the motor fuctuations of PD, and built classification and regression model to identify the motor symptoms levels.

HONORS & AWARDS

Best Paper Honorable Mention Award (top 5%), ACM UIST 2020	Aug 2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award (top 5%), ACM CHI 2020	Mar 2020
China National Scholarship for Doctoral students	Nov 2020
China National Scholarship for Undergraduates	Nov 2014

CCF Elite Collegiate Award	Oct 2015
Outstanding Graduates of Hunan Province	May 2016
ACM-ICPC Asia Regional Contest, Bronze Medal (Xi'an Site, Guangzhou Site)	Oct 2014-Nov 2014
National English Competition for College Students, Second Prize	May 2015
The second "Schlumberger" Cup Debug Competition, Winning Award	Dec 2016

SERVICES

Teaching Assistant UCAS - User Interface Design, Development & Evaluation (251M6008H) UCAS - Intelligent Human Computer Interaction (251M5009H)	Spring 2018 Fall 2017
Volunteer Public Science Day of Chinese Academy of Sciences @ISCAS National "Software and Network" Summer Camp for College Students @ISCAS ChineseCHI @Montreal, Canada	May 2019 Jul 2018 May 2018

Reviewing

Chinagraph 2018 / CHI 2020 / CHI LBW 2020 / ICMI 2020 / CHCI 2020 / CHI 2021